<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- this is version 6 of this xml2rfc template -->
<!--
    DOCTYPE processing

Some editors, such as XXE, resolve the ENTITY clauses before displaying the 
document to be edited.
-->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2223 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2223.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2578 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2578.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2579 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2579.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2580 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2580.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2629 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3410 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3410.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4181 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4181.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc strict="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>

<!-- Document  section 

Specify the category attribute per RFC2026 
options are info, std, bcp, or exp. 

docname is the name of the output document. This is optional;
the default is to use the base portion of the XML filename. 

For Internet-drafts, indicate which intellectual property notice 
to use. The value (as of this template) can be:
  --  trust200902
  --  noModificationTrust200902
  --  noDerivativesTrust200902 
  --  pre5378Trust200902 
The Intellectual Property section will be generated automatically by
XML2RFC, based on the ipr attribute in the rfc element.

If this document obsoletes an RFC, specify the RFC in the "obsoletes" attribute
If this document updates an RFC, specify the RFC in the "updates" attribute
-->
<rfc category="historic" docName="Your MIB Document name here rev06" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <!--
Enter the full document title and an abbreviated version
  to use in the page header.
-->

    <title abbrev="Your MIB Module document name">Your MIB module document name</title>

    <!-- copy the author block as many times as needed, one for each author.-->

    <!-- If the author is acting as editor, use the <role=editor> attribute-->

    <!-- see RFC2223 for guidelines regarding author names -->

    <author fullname="Editor name" initials="Y" role="editor"
            surname="Name">
      <organization>Editor affiliation</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Editor affiliation address</street>

          <city>Editor affiliation address</city>

          <country>Editor affiliation address</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>Editor address</phone>

        <email>Editor email</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <!-- month and day will be generated automatically by XML2RFC; 
be sure the year is current.-->

    <date  year="2010" />

    <!-- IETF area is optional -->

    <area>Operations &amp; Management Area</area>

    <!--WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc, 
IETF is fine for non-WG IETF submissions -->

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <keyword>Network Management</keyword>

    <keyword>Management Information Base</keyword>

    <keyword>MIB</keyword>

    <keyword>SMIv2</keyword>

    <!--add additional keywords here for IETF website search engine -->
<abstract>

<t> <cref>This template is for authors of IETF specifications containing MIB
  modules.  This template can be used as a starting point to produce
  specifications that comply with the Operations &amp; Management Area
  guidelines for MIB module internet drafts. Throughout the template, the marker "[TEMPLATE TODO]" is used as a placeholder to indicate an
  element or text that requires replacement or removal. All the places with [TEMPLATE TODO] markers 
  should  be replaced or removed before the document is submitted.</cref></t>
  
      <t>This memo defines a portion of the Management Information Base (MIB)
      for use with network management protocols. In particular it defines
      objects for managing [TEMPLATE TODO].</t>
      

 <t><cref>[TEMPLATE TODO]: describe what functionality will be managed using this MIB
 module. It can be good to mention the protocol being managed, and
 whether there is a particular aspect of the protocol to be managed, or a
 particular goal of the module. But keep it brief. Remember, don't put any citations 
 in the abstract, and expand your  acronyms. </cref></t>

 
</abstract>
 
    <note title="Foreword to template users">
      <t>This template is intended to help authors write the surrounding text needed in a
      MIB module internet draft, but does not provide a template for writing 
      the MIB module itself.</t>

      <t>Throughout this template, the marker "[TEMPLATE TODO]" is used as a reminder
      to the template user to indicate an element or text that requires
      replacement or removal by the template user before submission to the
      internet draft editor. All [TEMPLATE TODO] markers should be resolved and removed
      before you submit your document to the internet-draft editor.</t>

      <t>For updated information on MIB module guidelines and templates, see
      <xref target="RFC4181"></xref> and the OPS Area web page and wiki.</t>

      <t>For information on writing internet drafts or RFCs, see
      http://www.ietf.org/ietf/1id-guidelines.txt and 
      RFC2223(bis) <xref target="RFC2223"></xref>, and look
      at http://www.ietf.org/ID-Checklist.html for issues to note when writing
      drafts.</t>

      <t>This template is not meant to be a complete list of everything
      needed to write MIB module internet drafts, but to summarize the often-needed
      basic features to get a document containing a MIB module started. An
      important purpose of the template is to aid authors in developing an
      internet draft that is laid out in a manner consistent with other internet 
      drafts containing MIB modules. Internet drafts submitted for advancement 
      to the standards track typically require review by a MIB Doctor. This 
      template standardizes the layout and naming of sections, includes the 
      appropriate boilerplate text, and facilitates the development of tools 
      to automate the checking of MIB module internet drafts, to speed the WG 
      and IESG review processes.</t>

      <t>An XML2RFC template is also available. For information on XML2RFC, see
      RFC2629 <xref target="RFC2629"></xref>, and documentation available at
      http://xml.resource.org. The XML2RFC version includes
      advice describing how to fill in each section of the template. XML2RFC generates the 
      actual internet-draft from your information, and automatically handles getting up-to-date 
      boilerplates, references, and it handles many idnits issues.</t>

      <t>Within the template, there is reference to a SAMPLE-MIB; all references 
      to SAMPLE-MIB should be removed from your internet draft, and should be 
      replaced by references to your MIB module, as appropriate.</t>
      
      <t>[TEMPLATE TODO] THIS section, the complete section entitled "Note: Foreword to
      template users" should be removed by the template user from their
      document before submission.</t>

      <t>[TEMPLATE TODO] Remove all page headings from the template document, and
      replace them with the appropriate headings for your internet draft.</t>
    </note>
   
<note title="Note to RFC Editor re: [TEMPLATE TODO] markers">   
 <t>Note to RFC Editor: When a document is developed using this template, the editor of the 
  document should replace or remove all the places marked [TEMPLATE TODO] before submitting the document.
  If there are still [TEMPLATE TODO] markers, please send the document back to the editor.</t>
  </note>

   </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <!--You can echo the abstract in the Introduction, providing citations here, 
but you should provide more than just the abstract. -->

      <t>This memo defines a portion of the Management Information Base (MIB)
      for use with network management protocols. In particular it defines
      objects for managing the [TEMPLATE TODO].</t>

 <t><cref>[TEMPLATE TODO]: describe what functionality will be managed using this MIB
 module. Include citations for protocol specifications, architectures, related MIB modules, and protocol-specific
          management requirements. Provide an overview of why a MIB module is appropriate for this protocol,  whether there is a 
          particular aspect of the protocol to be managed, and how the module is expected to be used to 
          achieve particular goals. Highlight anything 'different' about the module. For example, 
          a read-only MIB module.</cref></t>

    </section>

    <section title="The Internet-Standard Management Framework">
      <t><cref>The title and text for this section has been copied from the 
official boilerplate, and should not be modified unless the official boilerplate text 
from the OPS Area web site has changed. See RFC4818 
section 3.1 for a discussion of the boilerplate section.</cref></t>

      <t>For a detailed overview of the documents that describe the current
      Internet-Standard Management Framework, please refer to section 7 of RFC
      3410 <xref target="RFC3410"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Managed objects are accessed via a virtual information store, termed
      the Management Information Base or MIB. MIB objects are generally
      accessed through the Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP). Objects
      in the MIB are defined using the mechanisms defined in the Structure of
      Management Information (SMI). This memo specifies a MIB module that is
      compliant to the SMIv2, which is described in STD 58, RFC 2578 <xref
      target="RFC2578"></xref>, STD 58, RFC 2579 <xref
      target="RFC2579"></xref> and STD 58, RFC 2580 <xref
      target="RFC2580"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Conventions">
      <t><cref>[TEMPLATE TODO] This boilerplate should be used if the RFC2119 key words 
are used in the internet draft. The text in this section has been 
copied from the official boilerplate, and should not be modified. </cref></t>

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
      
      </section>

    <!-- ********************************************* -->

    <section title="Overview">

     <t><cref>[TEMPLATE TODO] The narrative part should include an overview section that
   describes the scope and field of application of the MIB modules
   defined by the specification.  See RFC4181 section 3.2 for a
   discussion of the Narrative section.
</cref></t>

      <t></t>

      </section>


    <section title="Structure of the MIB Module">

    <t><cref>[TEMPLATE TODO] The narrative part SHOULD include one or more sections to
      briefly describe the structure of the MIB modules defined in the
      specification.</cref></t>


      <section title="Textual Conventions">

<t><cref>[TEMPLATE TODO] describe the textual conventions defined in the MIB
   module, and their purpose. It may be helpful to highlight any textual conventions
   imported from partner documents. Generic and Common Textual Conventions can be found summarized at 
the OPS Area web site. If there are no textual conventions used in your MIB module,
this section should be removed.</cref></t>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section title="The [TEMPLATE TODO] Subtree">

        <t><cref>[TEMPLATE TODO] copy this section for each subtree in the MIB module, and
        describe the purpose of the subtree. For example, "The fooStats subtree
        provides information for identifying fault conditions and performance
        degradation of the foo functionality."</cref></t>

      </section>

      <section title="The Notifications Subtree">

 <t><cref>[TEMPLATE TODO] describe the notifications defined in the MIB module, and
        their purpose. Include a discussion of congestion control. You might
want to discuss throttling as well. See RFC2914.</cref></t>

      </section>

      <section title="The Table Structures">

<t><cref>[TEMPLATE TODO] Describe the tables in the MIB module, their purpose, and their
reltionship to each other. If the row in one table is related to a row in 
another table, what happens when one of the rows is deleted? Should the 
related row be deleted as well? Consider both directions.</cref>
</t>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Relationship to Other MIB Modules">

<t><cref>[TEMPLATE TODO]: The narrative part should include a section that specifies the
relationship (if any) of the MIB modules contained in this internet drafts to
other standards, particularly to standards containing other MIB
modules. If the MIB modules defined by the specification import
definitions from other MIB modules or are always implemented in
conjunction with other MIB modules, then those facts should be noted in
the narrataive section, as should any special interpretations of objects
in other MIB modules. Note that citations may NOT be put into the MIB
module portions of the internet draft, but documents used for Imported items
are Normative references, so the citations should exist in the narrative
section of the internet draft. The preferred 
way to fill in a REFERENCE clause in a MIB module is of the form: "Guidelines 
for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs", RFC2434, section 2.3.</cref></t>

      <section title="Relationship to the [TEMPLATE TODO] MIB">

<t><cref>Example: The Interface MIB [RFC2863] requires that any
MIB module which is an adjunct of the Interface MIB clarify specific
areas within the Interface MIB. These areas were intentionally left
vague in the Interface MIB to avoid over-constraining the MIB, thereby
precluding management of certain media-types. Section 4 of [RFC2863] enumerates several
areas which a media-specific MIB must clarify. The implementor is
referred to [RFC2863] in order to understand the
general intent of these areas.</cref></t>

      </section>

     <section title="MIB modules required for IMPORTS">

<t><cref>[TEMPLATE TODO]: Citations are not permitted within a MIB module, but any
module mentioned in an IMPORTS clause or document mentioned in a
REFERENCE clause is a Normative reference, and must be cited someplace
within the narrative sections. If there are imported items in the MIB
module, such as Textual Conventions, that are not already cited, they
can be cited in text here. Since relationships to other MIB modules
should be described in the narrative text, this section is typically
used to cite modules from which Textual Conventions are imported. Example: "The following MIB module IMPORTS objects from SNMPv2-SMI [RFC2578], 
SNMPv2-TC [RFC2579],
SNMPv2-CONF [RFC2580], and IF-MIB [RFC2863]."</cref></t>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Definitions">
 <t><cref>This section contains the actual MIB module(s).
   These MIB modules MUST be written in SMIv2 [RFC2578] [RFC2579]
   [RFC2580]. See Section 4 of RFC 4181 for guidelines on SMIv2 usage. 
See Appendix C of RFC 4181 for suggested naming conventions.</cref></t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
[TEMPLATE TODO]: put your valid MIB module here. 
A list of tools that can help automate the process of 
checking MIB definitions can be found at the OPS 
Area web site.]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">

<t><cref>[TEMPLATE TODO] Each internet draft that defines one or more MIB modules MUST
contain a section that discusses security considerations relevant to
those modules. This section MUST be patterned after the latest approved
template (available at the OPS Area web site).
</cref></t>

<t><cref>[TEMPLATE TODO] if you have any read-write and/or read-create objects, please
include the following boilerplate paragraph, and list.the objects and their sensitivity.</cref></t>


      <t>There are a number of management objects defined in this MIB module
      with a MAX-ACCESS clause of read-write and/or read-create. Such objects
      may be considered sensitive or vulnerable in some network environments.
      The support for SET operations in a non-secure environment without
      proper protection can have a negative effect on network operations.
      These are the tables and objects and their
      sensitivity/vulnerability:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t></t>

          <!--
<t><cref>[TEMPLATE TODO] writeable tables and managed objects that could be especially disruptive
if abused and the associated security risks should be spelled out; RFC 2669 has a very good
example.</cref></t>
          -->
        </list></t>

<t><cref>[TEMPLATE TODO] else if there are no read-write or read-create objects in your MIB module,
use the following boilerplate paragraph.</cref></t>

      <t>There are no management objects defined in this MIB module that have
      a MAX-ACCESS clause of read-write and/or read-create. So, if this MIB
      module is implemented correctly, then there is no risk that an intruder
      can alter or create any management objects of this MIB module via direct
      SNMP SET operations.</t>

      <t><cref>For all MIB modules you must evaluate whether any readable objects
      are sensitive or vulnerable (for instance, if they might reveal customer
      information or violate personal privacy laws such as those of the
      European Union if exposed to unathorized parties). If so, please include the
following boilerplate paragraph.</cref></t>

      <t>Some of the readable objects in this MIB module (i.e., objects with a
      MAX-ACCESS other than not-accessible) may be considered sensitive or
      vulnerable in some network environments. It is thus important to control
      even GET and/or NOTIFY access to these objects and possibly to even
      encrypt the values of these objects when sending them over the network
      via SNMP. These are the tables and objects and their
      sensitivity/vulnerability: <list style="symbols">
          <t></t>

<t><cref>[TEMPLATE TODO] you should explicitly list by name any readable objects that
are sensitive or vulnerable and the associated security risks should
be spelled out (for instance, if they might reveal customer
information or violate personal privacy laws such as those of the
European Union if exposed to unathorized parties).</cref></t>

        </list></t>

<t><cref>[TEMPLATE TODO] The following three boilerplate paragraphs
should not be changed without very good reason. Changes will almost
certainly require justification during IESG review.</cref></t>

      <t>SNMP versions prior to SNMPv3 did not include adequate security. Even
      if the network itself is secure (for example by using IPsec), even then,
      there is no control as to who on the secure network is allowed to access
      and GET/SET (read/change/create/delete) the objects in this MIB
      module.</t>

      <t>It is RECOMMENDED that implementers consider the security features as
      provided by the SNMPv3 framework (see <xref target="RFC3410"></xref>,
      section 8), including full support for the SNMPv3 cryptographic
      mechanisms (for authentication and privacy).</t>

      <t>Further, deployment of SNMP versions prior to SNMPv3 is NOT
      RECOMMENDED. Instead, it is RECOMMENDED to deploy SNMPv3 and to enable
      cryptographic security. It is then a customer/operator responsibility to
      ensure that the SNMP entity giving access to an instance of this MIB
      module is properly configured to give access to the objects only to
      those principals (users) that have legitimate rights to indeed GET or
      SET (change/create/delete) them.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">

<t><cref>[TEMPLATE TODO] In order to comply with IESG policy as set forth in
http://www.ietf.org/ID-Checklist.html, every Internet-Draft that is
submitted to the IESG for publication MUST contain an IANA
Considerations section. The requirements for this section vary depending
what actions are required of the IANA. See "Guidelines for Writing an IANA 
Considerations Section in RFCs" [RFC2434]. and see RFC4181 section 3.5 for more
information on writing an IANA clause for a MIB module internet draft.</cref></t>

      <t>Option #1:</t>

      <figure>
        <preamble></preamble>

        <artwork><![CDATA[
     The MIB module in this document uses the following IANA-assigned
     OBJECT IDENTIFIER values recorded in the SMI Numbers registry: 
      
     Descriptor        OBJECT IDENTIFIER value
     ----------        -----------------------
     sampleMIB         { mib-2 XXX }
      	]]></artwork>

        <postamble></postamble>
      </figure>

      <t></t>

      <t>Option #2:</t>

      <t>Editor's Note (to be removed prior to publication): the IANA is
      requested to assign a value for "XXX" under the 'mib-2' subtree and to
      record the assignment in the SMI Numbers registry. When the assignment
      has been made, the RFC Editor is asked to replace "XXX" (here and in the
      MIB module) with the assigned value and to remove this note.</t>

      <t>Note well: prior to official assignment by the IANA, an internet
      draft MUST use placeholders (such as "XXX" above) rather than actual
      numbers. See RFC4181 Section 4.5 for an example of how this is done in
      an internet draft MIB module.</t>

      <t>Option #3:</t>

      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- The Author's Addresses section will be generated automatically by XML2RFC 
    from the front information. -->

    <section title="Contributors">
      <!--

      <t><cref>[TEMPLATE TODO] This optional section can be used to mention contributors to your internet draft.</cref></t>
      -->
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>

    <!-- References Section -->

    <!-- Section 4.7f of [RFC2223bis] specifies the requirements for the
   references sections.  In particular, there MUST be separate lists of
   normative and informative references, each in a separate section.
   The style SHOULD follow that of recently published RFCs.

   The standard MIB boilerplate available at
  the OPS Area web site includes lists of
   normative and informative references that MUST appear in all IETF
   specifications that contain MIB modules.  If items from other MIB
   modules appear in an IMPORTS statement in the Definitions section,
   then the specifications containing those MIB modules MUST be included
   in the list of normative references.  When items are imported from an
   IANA-maintained MIB module the corresponding normative reference
   SHALL reference the on-line version of that MIB module.  It is the
   policy of the RFC Editor that all references must be cited in the
   text;  such citations MUST appear in the overview section where
   documents containing imported definitions (other than those already
   mentioned in the MIB boilerplate) are required to be mentioned (cf.
   Section 3.2).

In general, each normative reference SHOULD reference the most recent
version of the specification in question.
-->

    <references title="Normative References">
        <!-- [TEMPLATE TODO] rfc2119, 2578, 2579, and 2580 are required to support MIB
      module boilerplate text. -->

      &rfc2119;

      &rfc2578;

      &rfc2579;

      &rfc2580;

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

<!--  RFC3410 is required to support the boilerplate text.-->
      &rfc2223;
      &rfc3410;

     &rfc2629;

       &rfc4181;

    </references>
    
    <references title="URL References">
<reference anchor="idguidelines">
	<front>
		<title>http://www.ietf.org/ietf/1id-guidelines.txt</title>
		<author>
			<organization>IETF Internet Drafts editor</organization>
		</author>
		<date year=""></date>
	</front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="idnits">
	<front>
		<title>http://www.ietf.org/ID-Checklist.html</title>
		<author>
			<organization>IETF Internet Drafts editor</organization>
		</author>
		<date year=""></date>
	</front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="xml2rfc">
	<front>
		<title>http://xml.resource.org</title>
		<author>
			<organization>XML2RFC tools and documentation</organization>
		</author>
		<date year=""></date>
	</front>
</reference>								
<reference anchor="ops">
	<front>
		<title>http://www.ops.ietf.org</title>
		<author>
			<organization>the IETF OPS Area</organization>
		</author>
		<date year=""></date>
	</front>
</reference>		
<reference anchor="ietf">
	<front>
		<title>http://tools.ietf.org</title>
		<author>
			<organization>IETF Tools Team</organization>
		</author>
		<date year=""></date>
	</front>
</reference>						
     
    </references>
    <!--
<section anchor="appendix" title="Appendix A">
	<t>You can add appendices just as regular sections, the only
difference is that they go under "back" element, and get letters 
instead of numbers</t>
</section>
-->

    <section title="Change Log ">
      <t>Note to RFC Editor: if this document does not obsolete an existing RFC, 
      please remove this appendix before publication as an RFC.</t>
<!--
      from draft 12 to draft 13
      <t><list style="numbers">
      <t></t>
        </list></t>
          -->
    </section>

    <section title="Open Issues">
      <t>Note to RFC Editor: please remove this appendix before publication as an RFC.</t>
           <!--
		 <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>Contributor addresses need to be updated</t>
        </list></t>
        -->
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>